<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
  <array name="tao_te_ching">
    <item>1. The Tao that can be told is not the eternal Tao. The
    name that can be named is not the eternal name. Unnameable is
    the essence. Naming is the beginning of ten thousand particular
    things. Named are the manifestations. Nameless is the
    Mystery.</item>
    <item>2. Whenever there is beauty there is ugliness. Whenever
    there is good there is bad. Long and short complete each other.
    High and low support each other. Difficult and easy need each
    other. Sound and silence fulfill each other. Front and back
    follow each other. Form and space shape each other. Life and
    death give birth to each other. Manifestations and Mystery come
    from the same source.</item>
    <item>3. Be one with the Tao. Act without forcing. Teach by
    showing. Things come let them come. Things go let them go. Give
    birth without possessing, achieve without expecting, create
    without taking credit, work without needing praise. Complete
    your work, then forget it. Your work lasts forever.</item>
    <item>4. The Tao is like a fertile valley, filled with
    creativity, Gateway of the Female, roots of Heaven and
    Earth.</item>
    <item>5. The Tao is like a well, empty but inexhaustible, dark,
    enduring, deep, ancestor of ten thousand things. However much
    you use it, you never have to fill it. However much you use it,
    you never use it up.</item>
    <item>6. Edge without sharpness, knot without tangle, hole
    without emptiness, door without opening. Soft glare. Clear fog.
    Submerged, indistinct, motherless, older than the gods.</item>
    <item>7. Thirty spokes, a rim, and a hub make a wheel. The hole
    in the center moves the cart. Clay molds into a pot. The
    emptiness inside holds the food. Roof, walls, and floor frame a
    house. The space within is where we live. Existence gives the
    form. Nonexistence gives the meaning.</item>
    <item>8. Look for it and you cannot see it. Listen for it and
    you cannot hear it. Reach for it and you cannot touch it. Grasp
    at it and you cannot hold it. Approach it and it has no
    beginning. Follow it and it has no end.</item>
    <item>9. When the superior hear about the Tao, they immediately
    endeavor to practice it. When the average hear about the Tao,
    they try it part way. When the lesser hear about the Tao, they
    laugh. That is why they are lesser, and the Tao is the
    Tao.</item>
    <item>10. Seek, and with this you will find. If you have
    committed wrongs, with this you will escape.</item>
    <item>11. For the good, their treasure. For the bad, their
    refuge.</item>
    <item>12. The Tao is impartial. It gives birth to both good and
    evil. Be impartial. Use whatever life sends.</item>
    <item>13. Heaven covers. Earth supports. Heaven and Earth
    endure.</item>
    <item>14. In living, honor the land. In thinking, be deep. In
    speaking be truthful. In working, be skillful. In dealing with
    others, be compassionate. In giving, be generous. In ruling be
    fair. In acting, be timely.</item>
    <item>15. The ten thousand things are female on one side and
    male on the other. Using both creates vitality. Balancing both
    creates harmony.</item>
    <item>16. Know the male but hold to the female. Know the white
    but hold to the black. Know the peaks but hold to the valleys.
    Know complexity but hold to simplicity. Know sound but hold to
    silence. Know action but hold to stillness. Know knowledge but
    hold to innocence. Know the manifestations but hold to the
    mystery.</item>
    <item>17. Activity counters cold. Tranquility counters
    heat.</item>
    <item>18. The Tao is the Great Mother. The ten thousand things
    are all her children. Know the Mother and you will know the
    children. Know the children and you will know the
    Mother.</item>
    <item>19. First we name. Then we describe. Then we compare.
    Then we set one first, another last. As soon as we start to
    name it is time to stop.</item>
    <item>20. Fill yourself with utmost emptiness. Embrace internal
    tranquility. The ten thou- sand things, see how they arise and
    flow around you each one coming into being, growing, adapting,
    changing, fulfilling, then returning to the source as you sit
    in stillness in the center, watching.</item>
    <item>21. Be aware, observe, notice. Appreciate the small. Find
    flavor in the delicate.</item>
    <item>22. Live wood is soft and tender. Dead wood is hard and
    strong. The live leaf is supple. The dead leaf is brittle. The
    army that is not flexible never wins a battle. The tree that
    survives the storm is the one that bends in the wind.</item>
    <item>23. Yield and prevail. If you can bend, you can be
    preserved unbroken. If you can flex, you can be kept straight.
    If you can be emptied, you can be filled. If you can be worn
    out, you can be renewed. Those with little can receive much.
    Those with much can be confused.</item>
    <item>24. The Tao is like water. Water takes the lowest way. It
    flows around obstacles. It has no projections, but it
    penetrates that which has no crevices. It is the softest of all
    things, but it grinds rock. It resists nothing, but is
    irresistible. It asks for nothing, but nourishes everything. It
    strives for nothing, but transforms everything.</item>
    <item>25. One who is one with the Tao is like a newborn boy
    child. His body is soft and pliant but his grasp is strong. He
    does not yet know the union of male and female, but his organ
    stands up. He can scream all day without getting hoarse or
    sleep utterly peacefully. He does just what he should be doing
    at each moment. He is completely natural.</item>
    <item>26. Be cautious, like one who fords a river in winter
    careful, like one restrained in speaking formal, like a host
    courteous, like a guest generous, like a fertile valley plain,
    like uncarved wood natural, like a tree in the wilderness calm
    and serene, like a still pool of deep water.</item>
    <item>27. Be detached. Work with joy, without caring for the
    achievement. Travel with joy, without focusing on the
    destination.</item>
    <item>28. On disaster good fortune perches. Beneath good
    fortune disaster crouches. Straight becomes crooked, which
    becomes straight again. Good gives rise to evil, which gives
    rise to good again. There is no beginning or ending.</item>
    <item>29. The bright way may seem dark. The straight way may
    seem crooked. The smooth way may seem rough. The way forward
    may seem to go backward. True love may seem heartless. True
    integrity may seem dishonest. True fullness may seem empty. And
    even the eternal may seem to change.</item>
    <item>30. Sincere words may not be beautiful. Beautiful words
    may not be sincere. The wise may not be learned. The learned
    may not be wise. The good may not be rich. The rich may not be
    good. Those who know may not speak. Those who speak may not
    know.</item>
    <item>31. Success is as treacherous as failure. Praise is as
    useless as blame. Fortune, fame, and favor are as dangerous as
    disgrace. High status and position can bring you great
    affliction.</item>
    <item>32. You can lose by gaining. You can gain by
    losing.</item>
    <item>33. Trapped in desires, you see only your desires.
    Trapped in desires, you see surfaces. Free from desires, you
    see the subtleties. Free from desires, you experience the
    mystery.</item>
    <item>34. Look to achievement for satisfaction and you will
    never be satisfied. Look to riches for contentment and you will
    never be content. Look to possessions for happiness and you
    will never be happy. Look to position for security and you will
    never be secure. Appreciate what you have. Rejoice in how
    things are. You lack nothing when you realize there is nothing
    lacking.</item>
    <item>35. Practice non-knowing. You do not know what is good
    and what is evil. So cleanse your mind of desire for particular
    ends, and accept everything, and let everything happen, and
    take joy in everything, and use everything that comes your
    way.</item>
    <item>36. To know that you know not is sanity. To know not that
    you know not is sickness. Be your own healer. Cure yourself of
    false knowing.</item>
    <item>37. Heal the people. Teach them non-knowing. When people
    think they know, they can not be guided. When people know that
    they do not know, they can find their own way.</item>
    <item>38. Desire not to desire. Value what is everywhere. Learn
    what to unlearn. Return to what the masses pass by.</item>
    <item>39. Put yourself last and be first, put yourself below
    and be above, give up personal desires and find all desires
    satisfied, gives up self interest and find interests realized,
    let go of everything and be one with everything, empty yourself
    completely and be completely fulfilled.</item>
    <item>40. In seeking knowledge, day by day something is added.
    In following Tao, day by day something is dropped. Day by day
    you do less and less deliberately. Day by day you do not do
    more and more. You do less and less and do not do more and
    more, until everything happens spontaneously. Then you act
    without acting, and do without doing, and achieve without
    forcing. And nothing is done. And nothing is left
    undone.</item>
    <item>41. Muddy water, when still, gradually becomes clear. Be
    still. Let your mud settle and your mind clear. Wait quietly
    until the right action comes naturally.</item>
    <item>42. Grasp at something and lose it. Act with purpose and
    defeat the purpose.</item>
    <item>43. The soldier who goes out ready to die comes back with
    life and victory. The soldier who goes out caring mostly for
    living dies and is forgotten.</item>
    <item>44. Heaven favors who knows what or why? Bravery may lead
    to death and loss. Caution may lead to life and victory.
    Without fighting you can be good at winning. Without speaking
    you can be good at responding. Without deliberateness you can
    be good at planning. No one summons the Tao. It comes on its
    own. Heavens net is vast and cast wide, and nothing slips
    through.</item>
    <item>45. Do not act on the ten thousand things. Simply help
    them be themselves. Do not try to change the people. Simply
    show them who they are. Lead them back to where they came from.
    Lead them back to what they have always known.</item>
    <item>46. Do not speak. Act. Do not teach. Show. When you rule,
    people hardly know you are there. When your work is done,
    people say, Look! We did this! All by ourselves!</item>
    <item>47. Be impartial. Be good to the good. Be good to the
    bad. Such is true good.</item>
    <item>48. The good teach. The bad are the raw material. Cherish
    the teacher and the raw material.</item>
    <item>49. Insincere words can be bought and sold. Empty deeds
    can be used as gifts. Things we see as bad should they ever be
    rejected? People we see as bad should they ever be
    abandoned?</item>
    <item>50. Know the tally, but do not call for the rewards or
    punishments. Those with virtue can do the accounting. Those
    without virtue collect the taxes.</item>
    <item>51. Accept everyone as children of the Tao, and treat
    everyone with compassion, generosity, and understanding.</item>
    <item>52. The world says I am great, but strange. If I were not
    strange, I could not be great. If I were like everyone else, I
    would be insignificant.</item>
    <item>53. Something there is that formed out of Chaos pure and
    deep and still standing alone, unchanging Mother of Heaven and
    Earth. I do not know its name. I only call it Tao.</item>
    <item>54. I have three treasures I hold and cherish:
    compassion, frugality, and not needing to be ahead of all under
    heaven. Compassion gives me courage. Frugality allows
    generosity. Not needing to be ahead lets me lead the
    people.</item>
    <item>55. Other people are noisy and exuberant. I am silent
    like something that has not yet given any sign like a baby who
    has not yet smiled. Other people have many possessions. I have
    nothing. Other people know where they are going and what they
    are doing. I am ignorant. Other people judge things and make
    many fine distinctions. I find everything subtle and complex.
    Other people act with purpose. I drift and float. Formless am I
    like the ocean shapeless, unmoving, unresting. I suck from the
    breast of the Mother.</item>
    <item>56. Heaven covers everything. Can you be as generous?
    Earth supports everything. Can you be as tolerant?</item>
    <item>57. Can you play the part of the female? Can you accept,
    allow, adapt, flex, bend, change? Can you use everything that
    comes your way?</item>
    <item>58. Can you be natural and spontaneous? Can you be like a
    newborn babe?</item>
    <item>59. Can you love the people? Can you teach and lead and
    serve them? Can you love them without trying to change them?
    Can you lead them and leave them free?</item>
    <item>60. Can you embrace the One? Can you cleanse and polish
    and purify the bright mirror of your soul? Can you concentrate
    and focus your breath and energy? Can you step outside yourself
    and understand all within the four reaches?</item>
    <item>61. Give birth without owning. Love without possessing.
    Teach without making dependent. Lead without trying to control.
    Act by helping things happen naturally. Guide by helping things
    grow naturally. Empty yourself, and let the Tao fill you and
    move through you and use you as part of the pattern.</item>
    <item>62. The Tao takes no action. Yet everything happens. If
    leaders could hold to it, the world would transform
    spontaneously. If, after the transformation, some wanted to
    take action, I would calm them with nameless simplicity.</item>
    <item>63. If I had just the smallest speck of wisdom, I could
    walk on the Great Way, and the only fear I would have would be
    of going astray. The Great Way is straight and smooth and easy
    to follow. But people delight in the crooked and rough and
    difficult.</item>
    <item>64. My words are easy to understand and easy to put into
    practice. But few understand, and few put them into
    practice.</item>
    <item>65. If everyone understood, what use would I be? It is
    because few understand that I can be of great value.</item>
    <item>66. A few will stop to hear about the Tao. Everyone will
    stop for food or music.</item>
    <item>67. The light rests on the heavy. The mountain grows from
    the valley. The noble is rooted in the common. Clear water
    floats over mud. Know your roots. Love, understand, and honor
    ordinary people.</item>
    <item>68. In expression, to be brief is natural. A whirlwind
    does not last all morning. A cloudburst does not last all
    day.</item>
    <item>69. Boasting and bragging are extra food and unnecessary
    baggage. They impede traveling on the Way.</item>
    <item>70. Self praise is no praise. When you describe an
    imaginary carriage, dream as you wish, embellish as you want,
    enumerate all the features as you will there is still no
    carriage.</item>
    <item>71. A jade necklace shines brightly, displays itself for
    everyone, jingles constantly. Be not like the jade. Just rumble
    occasionally like a rock.</item>
    <item>72. Give yourself to others, then be even greater. Use
    what you have for others, then have even more. The Tao nurtures
    everything and harms nothing. Help all and hurt none.</item>
    <item>73. Give, but do not give yourself away. Serve, but serve
    yourself first. The best commander is not killed or captured.
    How could the armies prevail without the commander?</item>
    <item>74. Travel all day without ever losing sight of your
    baggage. When safely within a walled in hostel, relax and
    transcends all cares.</item>
    <item>75. Look for virtue and success, and you find them
    everywhere. Look for failure and loss, and they constantly
    befall you.</item>
    <item>76. Use the Way as the means, and the end will be one
    with the Way. Follow the Way and the Way will be straight
    before you.</item>
    <item>77. Too much light causes blindness. Too much sound
    causes deafness. Too much indulgence in physical pleasures
    causes distraction and dissipation. Having too many possessions
    impedes traveling on the Way.</item>
    <item>78. Hold to the center. Dwell in the substance, not in
    the surface, in the fruit, not in the flower, in reality, not
    in appearances, in the essence, not in the ornament.</item>
    <item>79. Fill your cup too full and it will spill. Sharpen
    your knife too much and it will blunt. Acquire too much and you
    will be unable to protect it. Climb too high and you will be
    unable to maintain it. Too much pride brings on its own
    disaster. Too much study leads to exhaustion. More words mean
    less. Walk too far and you will pass your destination.</item>
    <item>80. The skillful carver does little cutting. The skillful
    traveler leaves few tracks and traces. The skillful binding
    takes few knots, but does not come undone. The skillful speaker
    uses few words.</item>
    <item>81. Be sharp, but do not cut. Be pointed, but do not
    pierce. Be straightforward, but not unrestrained. Be bright,
    but do not dazzle.</item>
    <item>82. The greatest mistake is desiring too much. The
    greatest sorrow is not knowing when you have enough. The
    greatest fault is needing to compete. The greatest defect is
    not knowing when to stop.</item>
    <item>83. Stop trouble before it starts. Make order before
    there is chaos. Deal with the small before it is large. Deal
    with the few before they are many. Begin the difficult while it
    is easy. Approach the great work through a series of small
    tasks. The largest evergreen grows from a tiny seedling. The
    journey of a thousand miles starts with a single step.</item>
    <item>84. If you rush into action, you may stumble. If you
    stand on tiptoe you do not stand stable. Failure comes most
    often near completion. Be as careful at the end as the
    beginning.</item>
    <item>85. One who is one with the Tao acts without acting. One
    who is less with the Tao acts with purpose. The greatest self
    is not self conscious. The lesser self is always aware of
    itself. The greatest integrity is spontaneous. The lesser
    integrity is deliberate. The greatest virtue is unaware of
    virtue. The lesser virtue never loses sight of virtue.</item>
    <item>86. To know others is knowledge. To know Self is wisdom.
    To control others shows power. To control Self is to be truly
    powerful. To know when you have enough is to be rich. To know
    when to act is to act appropriately. To know when to hold your
    place is to endure. To live at one with the Tao is to live
    forever.</item>
    <item>87. You cannot get too close to the Tao. You cannot shun
    the Tao. You can not help the Tao. You cannot harm the Tao. You
    can not ennoble the Tao. You can not debase the Tao. The Tao is
    the noblest thing under heaven.</item>
    <item>88. The best leader is invisible. The next best is loved
    and praised. The next is feared. The worst is ridiculed.</item>
    <item>89. The best warrior is not warlike. The best fighter is
    not aggressive. The best commander avoids combat. The best
    ruler serves the people.</item>
    <item>90. Ruling a large state is like frying a small fish.
    Cook it too much and you ruin it. Poke at it too much and it
    falls apart.</item>
    <item>91. When government is weak and invisible, people are
    open and honest. When government is powerful and interfering,
    people are secretive and devious.</item>
    <item>92. Too many taxes and the people starve. Too many rules
    and regulations and the people chafe and fret. When there is
    too much reward for success or too little room for succeeding,
    people will compete desperately. When goods are priced too high
    or wages too low, people will steal. When they are constantly
    shown good things they cannot have, people will rebel.</item>
    <item>93. When mansions are kept very clean, and rich people
    wear fine clothes, and carry sharp swords, and gorge themselves
    on expensive foods, and have luxurious possessions while the
    fields of the poor are full of weeds, and in the villages, the
    granaries are empty this is thievery! This is not the
    Way!</item>
    <item>94. When the Way is lost, there is virtue. When virtue is
    lost there is humanity. When humanity is lost there is
    righteousness. When righteousness is lost, there is propriety.
    Propriety is the beginning of chaos. When people do not
    respond, it rolls up its sleeves and uses force.</item>
    <item>95. Killing people in place of the master executioner is
    like cutting wood in place of the head carpenter. Cut wood in
    place of the head carpenter, and you are likely to cut your own
    hands.</item>
    <item>96. When a nation loses the Way, weapons abound, and
    warhorses are stabled in the suburbs.</item>
    <item>97. Weapons are instruments of ill omen. They should
    never be made into things of beauty. To worship weapons is to
    glorify in killing.</item>
    <item>98. Do not deal in violence. Violence rebounds. Do not
    glorify in war. Use weapons only when there is no other choice.
    After war the famines come. Where armies go, thorns and
    brambles grow.</item>
    <item>99. The world is a sacred vessel. You cannot improve it.
    Act on it to improve it and you ruin it. Try to control it and
    you come to ruin.</item>
    <item>100. The Way of Heaven is like the flexing of a bow. The
    high is drawn down. The low is brought up. When the string is
    pulled, all the parts move.</item>
    <item>101. You do not need to leave home in order to see the
    world. You do not have to look out your window in order to find
    the way. The harder you search the less you find. The farther
    you go the less you see.</item>
    <item>102. See without looking, find without searching, and
    arrive without going anywhere.</item>
    <item>103. Build your foundation upon it. What is firmly
    founded cannot be torn down. Embrace it. What is embraced
    tightly will be held. Cultivate it in yourself. Nurture it in
    your family. Practice it in your city. Express it in your
    state. Spread it throughout the universe. Let it
    overflow.</item>
    <item>104. Square without corners, vessel without walls,
    soundless tone, formless image that is the shape of the Tao.
    Accept, allow, adapt, flex, bend, change that is the method of
    the Tao. Create, complete, fulfill, reverse, return, renew that
    is the movement of the Tao.</item>
    <item>105. Every particular thing is a manifestation of the
    Tao. The Tao gives rise to all things. The Tao fulfills them.
    To the Tao they return. That is why everything venerates the
    Tao. That is why we find the Tao when we look inside
    ourselves.</item>
    <item>106. There is a time for living and a time for dying, a
    time for planting and a time for reaping, a time for motion and
    a time for stillness, a time for working and a time for
    rest.</item>
    <item>107. The Tao gives birth to all things, nourishes them,
    shelters them, cares for them, comforts them, and in the end,
    receives them back into itself.</item>
  </array>
</resources>
